<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sastibe&#39;s Data Science Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sastibe&#39;s Data Science Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Worry: Google Only Checks Your Location Every 10 Minutes</title>
      <link>/2018/04/don-t-worry-google-location/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/don-t-worry-google-location/</guid>
      <description>I have a personal Google account, complete with gmail, gdrive and everything else. I first opened it up as a sort of spam email for all kinds of logins, but started to it use more and more due to its convenience. I was always slightly worried about the magnitude of data collected by Google on me, yet I never found a way to pinpoint exactly the extent of my slight worrying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking AWS Instances with MNIST classification</title>
      <link>/2018/03/benchmarking-aws-instances/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/benchmarking-aws-instances/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post I have shown you how to setup an AWS instance running the newest RStudio, R, Python, Julia and so forth, where the configuration of the instance can be freely chosen. However, there is quite a lot of possibilities of instance configurations out there: There are different instance classes (General Purpose, Compute Optimized, RAM Optimized, … ) and different instance sizes within these classes. For General Purpose, or t2, there are, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Motivations for Starting a Blog</title>
      <link>/2018/01/my-motivations-for-starting-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/my-motivations-for-starting-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>Hello world!
My name is Sebastian Schweer, and I am a Data Scientist. This job description is increasingly popular, but it is notoriously difficult to describe precisely, what that entails. Let me show you one of my favourite definitions:
Source.
 My job requires me to spend a lot of time each day writing code in varying languages, mostly R but also Python and SAS. This inevitably leads me to spend a lot of time thinking about both code as well as the process of programming itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a Scalable RStudio Instance in AWS</title>
      <link>/2018/01/setting-up-a-scalable-rstudio-instance-in-aws/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/setting-up-a-scalable-rstudio-instance-in-aws/</guid>
      <description>Assume you want to start to write R code (a very good decision, in my opinion) and you want to be able to write and test code whereever you are. Wouldn’t it be awesome if one could set up an environment that can be used for R coding independent of any device? Where all you need is a decent browser, a working internet connection and you’re good to go?
Obviously, that is the case.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>